Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is פ"ה, Peh Hey,
85, and we continue one, two, three, four, five, six lines off
of the top on פ"ה עמוד א'. Peh Hey Amud Aleph. And
we are dealing with this הלכה halacha about what, you know, המזבח
מקדש, hamizbeach mekadesh, what type of things when you put on the
altar, even if they're invalid, gets to stay on the altar. Okay,
and we had a whole debate about like what is the scope
of something that's connected to the altar, that wasn't a degree of
פסול, psul, but how much is it connected? Does it have to
be burned, even put on without being burned, animal sacrifices, even a
מנחה, mincha, and so on. Okay, and then that was before yesterday,
two days ago, and then yesterday we started getting into how invalid
does something have to be, where the basic line was פסולה בקודש
psulah bakodesh or not פסולה בקודש, psulah bakodesh, something which invalidity happened
unrelated to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you know, unrelated to a
ritual, or better also an easy way to think about it was,
was it when it was alive or, you know, something that could
happen to it when it was alive is not פסולה בקודש, psulah
bakodesh, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who basically excludes a handful of
other things, not at the end of the day wasn't fully clear
why it was specifically that, but he excludes the case about the
blood being spilled, well that you can sort of see anyway, the
blood being taken out and שחט shechted at night. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara continues on פ"ה עמוד א', Peh Hey Amud Aleph, six
lines from the top. אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, אימורי קדשים קלים שהעלו
לפני זריקת הדם לא ירדו נעשו לחמו של מזבח. imurei kodshim kalim
shehe'elu lifnei zrikas hadam lo yerdu, nasu lachmo shel mizbeach.
So we had this before when we were discussing something that would
be excluded from this הלכה, halacha, which was the קומץ kometz of
the מנחה mincha before it was put into a כלי שרת, klei
sharet, because then it was not fully designated yet to the altar.
And the גמרא Gemara compared that to this statement of עולא. Ulla.
And עולא Ulla says that קדשים קלים, kodshim kalim, the אימורים imurim
of קדשים קלים, kodshim kalim, if you put them on the altar
before the throwing of the blood, they're still considered connected to the
altar and they became the bread of the altar, which is another,
it's interesting the choosing of that different phrase rather than saying המזבח
מקדשן, hamizbeach mekadeshan, you know, so why exactly is he choosing this
new language, you know, this new language might make you think like
maybe the fire has to start burning it, but he doesn't say
that, we'll get that idea later. Okay, anyway and the חידוש chiddush
here is, is that even though to some degree this is also
not yet fully designated, the מנחה mincha the problem that it wasn't
fully designated is you didn't know which part was going on the
altar. Here by the אימורים imurim of קדשים קלים, kodshim kalim, there's
no מעילה me'ilah even by the אימורים imurim because קדשים קלים kodshim
kalim are fundamentally under the owner's control because they're going to be
eating the meat and so on, and it only is fully designated
to God, the אימורים, imurim, after the זריקת הדם zrikas hadam is
thrown. And nevertheless, says עולא, Ulla, they're connected enough to the altar
that if they're put on, they don't come down. Okay, so this
הלכה halacha of המזבח מקדש hamizbeach mekadesh applies to them.
So basically you might not have done any of the אימורים, imurim,
you know, at this proper time, because you could have put them
all on.
Yeah, exactly. אמר רב זירא אף אנן נמי תנינא שנשפך דמו ושיצא
דמו חוץ לקלעים. Amar Rav Zeira, af anan nami tanina, she-nishpach damo
vesheyatza damo chutz lakla'im. So you said קדשים קלים, kodshim kalim, what
about, so קדשי קדשים kodshei kodshim is obvious, it's even קדשים קלים
kodshim kalim where the אימורים imurim are not fully yet designated to
the מזבח. mizbeach. קדשי קדשים kodshei kodshim the אימורים imurim would be
מעילה, me'ilah, they totally already be God's under God's control. We taught
similarly, שנשפך דמו ושיצא דמו חוץ לקלעים. she-nishpach damo vesheyatza damo chutz
lakla'im.
So and that's at least according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon not
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, so let's work with רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
okay so if the blood got spilled, okay, or was brought out
of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and it's never going to be
thrown, it got invalid. So he makes an obvious קל וחומר, kal
vachomer, ומה התם דאם בא לזרוק אין לו לזרוק, uma hatam de'im
ba lizrok ein lo lizrok, in that case if he wanted to
throw the blood he couldn't, okay so this animal is never going
to get the blood thrown, אמרת אם עלו
לא ירדו, amarta im alu lo yerdu, if nevertheless it says and
presumably we're not distinguishing קדשי קדשים kodshei kodshim and קדשים קלים, kodshim
kalim, we're talking about all sacrifices, so even an animal that the
blood has been spilled, the blood has been taken out, it's never
going to get the blood thrown, once it's on the altar it
doesn't come down. So if that's true, הכא דאם בא לזרוק זורק,
hacha de'im ba lizrok zorek, in your case where you just haven't
gotten around to the blood yet, לא כל שכן lo kol sheken
certainly it's connected to the altar and therefore it would not come
down, you know, once it got put up. It's more connected, it
might actually have a right to go there. So the גמרא Gemara
says,
no. תרגמה אקדשי קדשים. Targema akodshei kodshim. You can't prove it from
our משנה, Mishna, maybe our משנה Mishna only talking about קדשי קדשים
kodshei kodshim and as we said, this הלכה halacha is more obvious
by קדשי קדשים kodshei kodshim because it's already fully designated to God,
there's מעילה me'ilah from the very outset and so on. By קדשים
קלים, kodshim kalim, the אימורים imurim only become fully God's as it
were after the זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam. So you can't prove it
from the משנה. Mishna. So now we're going to get into a
discussion, can you basically infer from the משנה Mishna that the משנה
Mishna is talking even about קדשים קלים? kodshim kalim? So the גמרא
Gemara says, one minute. הרי פסח דקדשים קלים הוא, harei pesach dekodshim
kalim hu, at the end it speaks about פסח, pesach, a פסח
pesach that was שחט shechted שלא לשמו shelo lishmo is another example,
and presumably that means until now we've been talking, since we mentioned
a specific example of פסח pesach at the end, it sounds like
until now we've been talking about everything including קדשים קלים. kodshim kalim.
So the גמרא Gemara says... תרגמא בשלא לשמו. targema beshelo lishmo. No,
the פסח Pesach example was only the case of שלא לשמו. shelo
lishmo. The other cases of spilling the blood, that would be limited
to קדשי קדשים. kadshei kodashim. So again, you can't totally prove it.
Okay? So גמרא Gemara says, תנא, tna, let's try again. וכולן שעלו
לגבי מזבח ירדו. vechulan she'alu legabei mizbe'ach yerdu. So this וכולן שעלו
לגבי מזבח ירדו. vechulan she'alu legabei mizbe'ach yerdu. If all these animals,
all animals, if you brought them, forget the question of invalid. You
brought them to the top of the altar, okay, don't שחט shacht
them at the top of the altar. Bring them down and שחט
shacht them at the bottom. That was the end of the משנה.
Mishnah. So what's וכולן, vechulan, all animals? So, and it says that
after it mentions the פסח. Pesach. Okay, when it was speaking about
the invalidities, it mentioned a פסח שלא לשמו. Pesach shelo lishmo. And
then it says, by the way, any of these animals, if they
were on the top, even if they weren't פסול pasul whatever, bring
them down. So that makes it sound like, so let's take a
look.
השחוטין לא ירדו. hashchutin lo yerdu. So the implication is, if they
were alive, bring them down. But if you שחט'ד shachted these at
the top of the altar, these types of animals we were talking
about, don't bring them down even if they had some of the
invalidities we were talking about. So גמרא Gemara says, וכולה אתו. vekula
atu. So גמרא Gemara says,
השחוטין לא ירדו. hashchutin lo yerdu. מאי לאו לא שנא קדשי קדשים
ולא שנא קדשי קלים. mai lav lo shena kadshei kodashim velo shena
kadshei kalin. So implicitly it's saying even if it's קדשי קלים, kadshei
kalin, if you שחט'ד shachted it at the top of the altar,
you keep it there and presumably even if it had some of
the invalidities that we were talking about, okay, or some blood spilled
or whatever. So גמרא Gemara says, לא, השחוטין מהם ירדו ומהם לא
ירדו. lo, hashchutin mehem yerdu umehem lo yerdu. No, don't make any
inference. Sometimes you wish the גמרא Gemara would say this like stop
with all the inferences, like just literally what I'm saying. No, we're
not dealing with a case if you שחט'ד shachted it. If you
שחט'ד shachted it and it was invalid, some would come down, like
the פסח, Pesach, and others would not come down, assuming that's how
we could hold not like ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. Okay, all we're
saying is that if they're alive, they have to come down. We're
not making any inference that if they're שחט'ד shachted they all get
to stay up, even the קדשי קלים. kadshei kalin. So גמרא Gemara
says, one minute.
וכולן קתני. vechulan ktani. But it says all of them get to
stay up. So גמרא Gemara says, כולן אחיין. chulan achayin. Okay, like
we're saying, did you hear what I said the first time? We're
not talking about the inference, okay? The משנה Mishnah there is no
inference meant. If they're שחט'ד shachted the הלכה halacha differs. When we're
saying is when they're alive, they all come down, and we're talking,
that's when we're talking about all animals, whether קדשי קדשים kadshei kodashim
or קדשי קלים. kadshei kalin. So now the גמרא Gemara is going
to say, okay, but if you're not here to teach me the
inference, isn't this הלכה halacha pretty obvious? So גמרא Gemara says, פשיטא.
pshita. So isn't this all obvious? So גמרא Gemara says, לעולם אחיין
ובדוקין שבעין. le'olam achayin ubedukin sheba'ayin. Okay, what?
17 in the whole thing, right.
So the חידוש chiddush is that they even if they're alive, but
there might be an invalidity. Now what could be the invalidity? Because
it can't have to, it can't be an invalidity that's like, I
don't know, רובע rove'ah or נרבע nirba or something of that nature,
because if that were true, even after you שחט'ד shachted him, you
would take it down, right? Because it has to be a type
of an invalidity that if you שחט'ד shachted it, you would get
to keep it up. So what would be the example of that?
But the one that was still around when it was alive. So
the only type of an invalidity that can be in the animal
when it's alive and that if you שחט'ד shachted it would get
to stay up there, okay, would be this minor blemish according to
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. We're going to see later, like some type
of a cataract of the eye, we'll get to it. But a
minor blemish according to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So that's now the
חידוש. chiddush. The חידוש chiddush is you take this animal with a
minor blemish. If it was שחט'ד, shachted, you would leave it up
there because we're going according to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. But because
it's alive, you bring it down. Now here's the חידוש. chiddush. The
חידוש chiddush is what's going to happen if you bring this down?
You bring this down, so first of all, you're not going to
שחט shacht it, okay? But if you accidentally, if you did שחט
shacht after you brought it down, you shouldn't have שחט'ד shachted because
it was a בעל מום, ba'al mum, but you did. Okay, can
you put the meat back up? No, right? You guys follow me?
It's got this small blemish. If it's alive, you bring it down.
Now, you שחט'ד shachted it when you brought it down. You shouldn't
have שחט'ד shachted because it was a בעל מום, ba'al mum, but
you did. Okay, can you put the meat back up? No. If
it's not on the altar, it doesn't get to be on the
altar. So you could have said leave it up on the altar
because then if you accidentally שחט, shacht, again you're not supposed to
שחט, shacht, but if you accidentally שחט, shacht, it'll be allowed to
be kept up there, okay. So the חידוש chiddush is even though
were you to שחט shacht it at the top of the altar,
you'd be allowed to keep it there because it's this small blemish,
nevertheless you're required to bring it down even though that means it's
not going to be able to get back up on the altar.
Which isn't such a חידוש chiddush because you're not supposed to be
שחט'ינג shachting it anyway. Yes.
In all these cases are we saying that let's say you did
it and whatever and it gets to stay on top of the
altar, then that's also good for the בעלים, ba'alim, he doesn't have
to bring...
No, no, no. All of this is just a הלכה halacha that
the stuff gets to burn on the altar. The owners do not
fulfill their obligation. They never fulfill their obligation with these invalidities. Okay,
well, I shouldn't say that. If the invalidity is in the blood,
they never fulfill their obligation. If the invalidity is in other things,
then it's just a question about what gets to be on the
altar, okay.
Right, so in this case of דוקין שבעין...
dukin sheba'ayin... No, because it's a בעל מום ba'al mum that the
פסול psul is in the גוף. guf. The פסול psul is in
the whole... isn't limited, isn't on something other than the blood. Okay?
It's on the whole קרבן. korban. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this. ובדוגין שבעין ואליבא דרבי עקיבא U-bedugin she-ba-ayin ve-aliba de-Rabbi Akiva
דאמר de-amar אם עלו לא ירדו. im alu lo yerdu. So that's
the חידוש. chiddush. Don't make any inferences about קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim
and what would be if it had a פסול psul blah blah
blah. The חידוש chiddush is it's alive and even though it's got
a small blemish, which wouldn't be a problem if it was שחט,
shechted, take it down off the altar. Now, במאי אוקימתא be-mai okimta
בפסולין. bi-psulin. Fine, you want to now say the חידוש chiddush of
the case if they're alive, bring them down, is talking about animals
that have פסול, psul, admittedly only one פסול, psul, small blemishes. Okay?
But that's what now the חידוש chiddush is of if they're alive,
keep them up there. Ah, excuse me, don't keep them up there,
bring them down. אימא סיפא, Eima seifa, let's look at the end
of the משנה. Mishnah. וכן עולה שעלתה חיה לראש המזבח תרד. Ve-chen
olah she-altah chayah le-rosh ha-mizbe'ach tiered. If you brought an עולה olah
to the top of the altar, bring it down.
שחטה בראש המזבח יפשיט וינתח במקומה. shachatah be-rosh ha-mizbe'ach yafshit vi-yenate'ach bi-mkomah.
So this is the end of the משנה. Mishnah. If you actually
שחט shechted it, flay it in that spot. Okay? So now it
says like this. ואי פסולה, ve-i psulah, one minute, so assuming now
when we're talking about stuff that got brought up the top of
the altar, the חידוש chiddush was even if it had a blemish,
right? That's now
the second part of the משנה Mishnah that they brought alive to
the top of the altar, you're saying the case is is that
it's got a blemish. All right?
So then it says if you שחט shechted an עולה olah at
the top of the altar, flay it there. So one minute, if
it's got a blemish, what are you doing flaying
it, you don't flay animals that have blemishes. You're not supposed to
be putting them on the fire. So presumably by the way, even
though the הלכה halacha would be that it gets to stay up
at the top according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, it's on the
altar, don't bring it down. Okay? So we're not debating that, you
did שחט shecht it, it had a blemish, for רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva it stays on the top etc., so that's the חידוש, chiddush,
שחט shechted it would stay up. If it's alive you bring it
down. So you would keep it up there, but you shouldn't be
flaying it. You don't go through that whole procedure.
So what do you do?
You just put it on the fire like it is. Okay?
Meaning no matter what it is, it's like, you know, so it's
my שלמים shlamim that goes up there.
Yeah.
So then... No, no, no, no. The meat of a שלמים shlamim
is not שייך shayach to the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Things that are שייך
shayach to the מזבח mizbe'ach stay up.
So they still have to do like הפשט וניתוח hefshet ve-nituach according
to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva then, right?
You mean because... yeah, but we're talking about an עולה. olah. Okay?
So שחטה בראש המזבח Shachatah be-rosh ha-mizbe'ach יפשיט וינתח במקומה. yafshit vi-yenate'ach
bi-mkomah. ואי פסולה בת הפשט וניתוח היא? Ve-i psulah bat hefshet ve-nituach
hi? If it's invalid, is it something deserving of being flayed and
cut up into pieces? ואותה
אמר רחמנא, Ve-osah amar Rakhamana, אותה כשירה ולא פסולה. osah kisherah ve-lo
psulah. Okay? And we have a דרשא drasha that is the only
thing that you flay and dismember is something that is כשירה, kisherah,
which is interesting by the way, because then like what do you
do? You put the whole carcass straight on the fire? You know,
I mean because it doesn't come down, right? Because that's the הלכה.
halacha. Right, but it sounds like you would put the whole carcass
straight on the fire. So the גמרא Gemara says סיפא אתאן לכשירה.
seifa atan le-kisherah. Fine. No, no, no. The end, when we're saying
if you שחט shechted the עולה olah flay it up there, we're
not talking about the case where it had a blemish. There's two
separate cases. If it's alive, bring it down even with a blemish.
If it's an עולה olah which was שחט shechted there, not with
a blemish, then dismember it up there. But we know that though.
So now the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
ומאי קמשמע לן? u-mai ka mashma lan? So what's it teaching us?
דיש הפשט וניתוח בראש המזבח. de-yesh hefshet ve-nituach be-rosh ha-mizbe'ach. It would
be teaching us that you are allowed to exactly this הלכה, halacha,
no inference, no חידוש, chiddush, no like no other הלכה, halacha, you
know, no surprise. It's teaching you if you שחט shechted an animal
at the top of the
altar or I don't know, somehow you brought the carcass to the
top of the altar, whatever you did, you're allowed to basically flay
it at the top of the altar. That's what it's teaching you.
So the גמרא Gemara says, so the גמרא Gemara says ומאי דיש
הפשט וניתוח בראש המזבח? ולמאן דאמר אין הפשט וניתוח בראש המזבח מאי
איכא למימר? U-le-man de-amar ein hefshet ve-nituach be-rosh ha-mizbe'ach mai ika le-meimar?
But one minute, says the גמרא. Gemara. There's an opinion that says
you don't flay things at the top of the altar. So according
to him, what's the חידוש? chiddush? Now just pause for a moment.
If you say you don't flay things at the top of the
altar, how do you explain our משנה? Mishnah? Our משנה Mishnah is
explicit, forget any inference. Okay? No, but the גמרא Gemara is saying
is what's the חידוש chiddush of the משנה Mishnah if you say
you don't flay things at the top of the altar? What do
you mean? The משנה Mishnah says you flay things at the top
of the altar. So if you say you don't, the חידוש chiddush
of the משנה Mishnah is that it doesn't agree with you. You
know what I'm saying? But the משנה Mishnah is pretty clear that
it says you flay things at the top of the altar. So
תוספות Tosafos says, תוספות Tosafos asks this question, and תוספות Tosafos says
that the point is like this.
Right, everybody agrees to the פשט pshat of the משנה. Mishnah. The
פשט pshat of the משנה Mishnah is something that was שחט shechted
at the top of the altar, you're allowed to flay it at
the top of the altar. The debate that the גמרא Gemara is
referring to, says תוספות, Tosafos, is that something was basically not שחט
shechted at the top of the altar and you want to either,
I don't know, לכתחילה li-chatchilah bring the carcass up to the top
of the altar, you know, maybe it's too crowded down there, or
you want to לכתחילה li-chatchilah bring it to the top... altar in
order to שחט shecht it, but not that it's already there, okay?
That's the debate whether you're allowed to do it. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, it's the גמרא Gemara says it's pretty obvious
again with the גמרא Gemara thinking things being obvious that if it's
already been שחט shechted at the top of the altar you're allowed
to flay it. So what would the חדוש chidush of the משנה
Mishna be? The חדוש chidush of the משנה Mishna would be to
imply that you're always allowed to flay it at the top of
the altar. This is the way תוספות Tosfos is reading it, I
don't know, because he's dealing with an obvious problem. How could you
say what's the חדוש chidush of the משנה Mishna if I don't
agree with the משנה? Mishna? You know, I mean the משנה Mishna
is explicit. So the way תוספות Tosfos is reading it is: Yes,
everybody agrees to the פשט pshat of the משנה Mishna that if
it's שחט shechted at the top of the altar you can flay
it. But my question is, but that's pretty obvious. So what's the
חדוש? chidush? So the חדוש chidush could be you're always allowed to
flay things at the top of the altar and even לכתחילה. lechatchilah.
Ah, but if you say you're not always allowed to flay things,
again what's the חדוש chidush of the משנה? Mishna? So just go
with it. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says, I'm not happy, to me
it doesn't seem like there's a big חדוש chidush to the משנה
Mishna if it's just that the animal is without a מום mum
and was שחט shechted there that you could flay it. Okay, that's
not a big חדוש. chidush. So מאי איכא למימר, mai ika lemeimar,
so what is the חדוש? chidush? So הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שהיתה
לו שעת הכושר ונפסלה. hacha bemai askinan kegon shehayta lo sha'at hakesher
venifsela. Fine, fine. The end will also be talking about a case
of a פסול. psul. Okay,
so one case is you got your live animal with your little
מום mum of the eye and the חדוש chidush is bring it
off the altar. And even though it's true had you שחט shechted
it on the altar you would be allowed to keep it there,
nevertheless, sorry Charlie, it is still alive, you're not allowed and you
got to bring it down. And you're not supposed to שחט shecht
it anyway. That's part one of the משנה. Mishna. When it says
if it's alive you bring it down. Part two, which it says
if an עולה olah is slaughtered that you flay it, okay, we
are also talking about a case of an invalidity. Not an invalidity
of a מום, mum, a different invalidity. Something that became invalid after
it was slaughtered. Let's say, I don't know, all the blood spilled,
okay, or let's say it became טמא, tamei, something that became invalid.
And the חדוש chidush is, you before said how could you flay
something that's invalid? That's the חדוש. chidush. The חדוש chidush is you're
allowed to flay it if there was a moment when it was
כשר kasher even though now it's פסול. pasul. Okay? רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון היא. Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon hi. It's רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון
Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon דאמר כיון שנזרק הדם והורצה בשר שעה אחת,
d'amar keivan shenizrak hadam vehurtzah basar sha'ah achat,
since if the blood was thrown and the meat became, you know,
permissible for one minute, יפשיטנה ועורו לכהנים, yafshetenah ve’oro lakohanim,
you could go and then the meat became טמא tamei or something
of that nature, you can still go ahead and flay it. And
what's the purpose of flaying it? Okay, if you're not going to
put the meat on the altar? His case is you didn't שחט
shecht it on the altar, you were at the bottom. You שחט
shechted an animal, okay, the blood was thrown and then the meat
became טמא. tamei. And for him you flay it. Why do you
flay it? The meat you're going to burn. You flay it so
the כהנים kohanim can still get the leather. That's expensive, the whole
leather of an עולה. olah.
Wait, if it's a שלמים shlamim though, would the בעלים be'alim get
it?
Yeah, I guess so. Yeah, you're right, I guess so. Okay, so
in our case as well,
hold on, we would be talking about...
oh so שעת הכושר, sha'at hakesher, I might have
misdescribed the example. I said you spilled the blood. The שעת הכושר
sha'at hakesher meant there was a moment when in theory it could
have been good, but it might mean like this according to this
case, that actually the blood was thrown. So you שחט shechted it
at the top of the altar, you threw the blood, and then
the meat let's say became טמא. tamei. That would be the simplest
scenario. Okay, so now what have we said? Remember, all of this
is in an attempt to prove or disprove whether or not our
משנה Mishna supports עולא, Ulla, whether or whether our משנה Mishna makes
עולא'ס Ulla's statement obvious. Is our משנה Mishna talking about קדשים קלים
kodashim kalim and telling you that even if you spill the blood
you get to, if the אימורין imurin were up there they get
to stay up there? Okay, that's basically, so in that context of
that argument of is the משנה Mishna talking about קדשים קלים, kodashim
kalim, we were discussing what's the end of the משנה Mishna when
it says live animals at the top, שחט shechted the עולה olah
at the top. And how what we've said is the following: Live
animals at the top is fundamentally the case the חדוש chidush is
the case where it's got a small מום mum and the חדוש
chidush is you still have to take it down even though had
it been dead you'd be allowed to leave it up there. And
the second part of the עולה, olah, the חדוש chidush is that
you are allowed to flay it even after it became invalid as
long as there was a moment when it was valid. Presumably the
blood was thrown and then something happened. You can continue to flay
it and because at the top of the altar you can actually
burn the meat on the altar, flay it and give it to
the כהנים. kohanim. Why are you allowed to do that, isn't it
invalid? Yes, but it was a moment when it was valid. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: ואלא דקתני כיצד עושה.
ve’ela de'katani keitzad oseh. But one minute, we got a ברייתא braisa
that says: Keitzad oseh, what do you do when you שחט shechted
this עולה olah at the top of the altar? Okay, what do
you do? מוריד את הקרביים למטה. morid et hakirbayim lemata. You take
the inner
organs down to the bottom. And the inner organs of course is
the small intestine which has all the refuse. ומדיחן, umadichan, and you
rinse them. Okay. So now, למה לי? lama li? So now remember
you said we were talking about a פסול עולה. pasul olah. Okay,
that's your point about how to read the משנה. Mishna. But if
it's פסול, pasul, as soon as you bring something off of the
altar... them? היכי עביד heichi avid you do that
for an עולה? olah? You take down the intestines and rinse them?
Well, don't you just like a normal עולה, olah, sure?
You always have the intestines... No, no.
You bring it today, you do not want to be burning that
on top of the altar. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
So היכי נעביד? heichi na'avid? So the גמרא Gemara says well, what
do you want me to do? נקריבהו? nakriveihu? You want me to
burn the intestines with all of the, you know, excrement on top
of the altar?
בפרתיה be'fartiya with its פרש, peresh, with its excrement? Should be like
a shin, right? Yeah, exactly. המקריבהו נא לפחתך? hakrivehu na l'fachatzecha?
Would you bring such a thing quoting a פסוק pasuk in מלאכי
Malachi which we use as a basis somehow saying that things that
are obviously disgusting you can't bring as a קרבן? korban? Would you
bring this to your governor? הירצך? hayirtzecha? Would this find favor for
you? או הישא פניך? o hayisa panecha? Would he lift up your
countenance? Would he show you favor? So how, of course you can't
burn it like this. גמרא Gemara says I know you can't burn
it like that. That wasn't my question. אנן הכי קאמרינן anan hachi
ka'amrinan and here's was my question. Assuming that it's invalid, what was
the point, not how you should burn it up there. If you
need, you can't burn it up there the way it is. But
then bring it down and throw it out. What's the point of
rinsing it? You're not going to be able to bring it back
up, right? Because it's a פסול pasul thing that's no longer on
the altar. מדיחן למה לי? madichan lama li? Why are you bothering
rinsing it? So right? Because you're not going to be able to
bring it back up. So the גמרא's Gemara's answer is, here's why
you would rinse it: דמשתמי כהן אחרינא ולא ידע ונסקינהו. d'mishtamei kohen
achrina v'lo yada u'naskinehu.
So it's like we're rinsing it so that accidentally maybe it might
get put back up. Like it's very funny, because what, you're not
allowed to, but like if some כהן kohen who was ignorant would
come ahead and say hey, why did somebody leave these intestines down
here? I'm going to help people out, I'll bring it up to
the top. Then now because it's rinsed out or whatever, even though
it was an invalid עולה olah it'll get to stay on the
top.
Okay? But isn't that like
intentionally, right?
Exactly. So that's a good question. I mean, this question comes up
sometimes in כשרות. kashrut. Like let's say I've got this spoon that
I טרפתי treif-ti up, right? So whatever. So now I have to
כשר kasher it. So you're not allowed to מבטלו לכתחילה. mevatlo lechatchila.
I can't throw it in my drawer with all my other spoons
and mix it up because whatever, that's מבטלו לכתחילה. mevatlo lechatchila. Question
if it works by spoons, is it a דבר שיש לו מתירים
davar sheyeish lo matirin but anyway, go with me. Anyway, can I
go ahead and leave it near, leave it on the side assuming
that my wife will come and say off that husband of mine
he never puts anything away and she'll put it away
and then it'll be שוגג shogeg and then it'll be מותר. mutar.
So that's an interesting discussion in the פוסקים, poskim, okay? So here's
a similar question. Let's just rinse it and just leave it there
and maybe some ignorant כהן kohen will come. So the גמרא Gemara
then pushes back, says you're not allowed to do that. You're not
allowed to play around with that. ואנן ניקו v'anan neiku says the
גמרא, Gemara, we're going to get up ונעביד להו לכהנים מילתא דאתו
בה לידי תקלה? v'na'avid lehu l'kohanim milta d'atu bah lidei takala? We're
going to go ahead and arrange something for the כהנים, kohanim, something
that could lead to doing something wrong? I mean, you know, it's
true, if you did it, it would be able to stay up
but you're not supposed to do it. And by rinsing it, we're
sort of greasing the wheels for this to get put on the
altar but you're not supposed to do that. So why again would
we, if we're talking about a פסול עולה, pasul olah, which is
what you said the case was, why are we rinsing out the
intestines? So גמרא Gemara says yes, we are going to rinse them
out. אפילו הכי עדיפא afilu hachi adifa שלא יהא קדשי שמים מוטלים
כנבלה. shelo yehei kodshei shamayim mutalim k'neveilah. Yes, we do not want
this stuff to be treated like some carcass and איכס, ichs, disgusting
intestines or whatever. Eventually what you're gonna have to do is you're
gonna have to burn it, right? That's what you do with this
stuff anyway, outside of the... yeah, whatever... actually כל שפסולה בקודש kol
shepsulah b'kodesh you burn in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. And I
wonder why the גמרא Gemara didn't say that either because it probably
would be disgusting, that smell. So anyway, since you're going to have
to burn this stuff like not on the altar, you wouldn't want
the refuse in it. But the גמרא Gemara says regardless even before
we get...
wait, but the refuse still gets burned, but just not on the
altar, right?
No, the גמרא Gemara says by, that's true, the גמרא Gemara says
that by פרים הנשרפים parim hanisrafim על פרשו ועל קרבו al pirsho
v'al kirbo etcetera, but not by פסול, pasul, not by these פסול
pasul קרבנות. korbanot.
I can double check but I'm pretty sure you take the refuse
outside of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Yeah, you just whatever, exactly.
That's my, that's my understanding, I can double check. Yeah, exactly.
Do they
have a note about that?
Well, they said that not about that specifically but the פסול pasul
items,
there is a fire inside.
Yeah, yeah, that I know but the question is what do you
do with the refuse? My understanding would be that that הלכה halacha
that you burn it with the refuse is only by קדשי... kodshei...
is only by
חטאת פנימיות. chatat penimiot. But I can double check that. But anyway,
so the גמרא's Gemara's basic answer is look, you rinse it out
because you don't want something that had been sanctified, even if it
can't go on the altar, to be sitting around in the dung.
And that's why we do it as a matter of respect. That's
certainly not פשט pshat of the ברייתא braita at all. פשט pshat
of the ברייתא braita is you're rinsing it out in order that
you can bring it back and put it back on the altar.
Anyway, but that's what the גמרא Gemara said, we can say the
end of the משנה mishnah is talking about various scenarios of פסולים
psulim and therefore the משנה mishnah doesn't have to be talking about
קדשים קלים. kodashim kalim. So the משנה mishnah is not obviously... teaching
you what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish taught you. So ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish is still an element of a חידוש chidush in ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish that’s not explicitly in the משנה. mishnah. Okay, and now
the גמרא Gemara says that a similar teaching of רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan or a question of
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan about the same issue that ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish dealt with. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא בעי רבי יוחנן, Amar
Rabbi Chiya bar Abba baei Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan asked,
אימורי קדשים קלים שהעלום לפני זריקת דמן, Eimurei kodshim kalim she'he'elum lifnei
zrikat daman, exactly ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish scenario, you have these intestines
that were brought up before the blood was thrown of קדשים קלים,
kodshim kalim, ירדו או לא ירדו, yerdu o lo yerdu, come do
they come down or not come down? Okay, so he, what ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish said פסקן paskinen they stay up, he didn’t know.
אמר ליה רבי אמי ותיבעי לך מעילה? Amar lei Rabbi Ami v'tiba'i
lach me'ilah? Why don’t you ask about מעילה? me'ilah? It’s the same
point, right? The אימורין eimurin of קדשים קלים kodshim kalim are not
fully God’s until זריקת הדם zrikat hadam because it’s all fundamentally under
the owner's control. That’s why there’s this question of do they stay
on the מזבח? mizbeach? So a similar question would be at what
stage do they become fully God’s in order to have the הלכה
halacha of מעילה? me'ilah? אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said back to
him,
מעילה לא קמיבעי לי דזריקה הוא דקבעה להו במעילה. Me'ilah lo kamiba'i
li d'zrika hu d'kava'ah lehu b'me'ilah. It’s clear to me that until
it really is totally fit for the מזבח, mizbeach, there’s no מעילה.
me'ilah. Okay, until that point it’s not fundamentally God's portion yet. כי
קמיבעי לי ירידה. Ki kamiba'i li yerida. What I want to know
is this issue of taking things down because you know what? There’s
a lot of things we keep on the מזבח mizbeach that shouldn’t
be there that we let stay up there. So that’s what I
want to know. I know that there’s not yet מעילה, me'ilah, it’s
not fully God’s portion, but maybe it’s close enough that it gets
to stay at the top of the מזבח, mizbeach, which actually is
the הלכה halacha according to ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. No מעילה me'ilah
but it stays at the top of the
מזבח. mizbeach. ופשיט לא ירדו דאין בהן מעילה, Upashit lo yerdu d'ein
bahen me'ilah, and he came to exactly ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish conclusion.
It doesn’t go down, it stays on the מזבח, mizbeach, and nevertheless
there’s not yet מעילה. me'ilah. Okay, it’s not fully enough God’s for
there to be מעילה, me'ilah, but it’s close enough that it stays
at the top of the מזבח. mizbeach. That was one version of
the debate and now another version very similar. רב נחמן בר יצחק
מתני הכי. Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak matni hachi.
Here’s how he teaches it. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא בעי רבי
יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba baei Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan asked, אימורי קדשים קלים שהעלום לפני זריקת דמן יש בהן מעילה
או לאו?
Eimurei kodshim kalim she'he'elum lifnei zrikat daman
yesh bahen me'ilah o lav? He wanted to know if there was
מעילה me'ilah or not in this case, that was his question, before
the blood was thrown. אמר ליה רבי אמי ותיבעי לך ירידה? Amar
lei Rabbi Ami v'tiba'i lach yerida? Why don’t you ask if they
don’t have to come off the מזבח? mizbeach? אמר ליה ירידה לא
קמיבעי לי דנעשו לחמו של מזבח, Amar lei yerida lo kamiba'i li
d'nasu lehu lachmo shel mizbeach,
throwing in ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish terminology here. Okay, no, that, it’s
obvious to me once it’s on the מזבח, mizbeach, it stays on
the מזבח. mizbeach. That, you know, the מזבח mizbeach is very good
at keeping things up there. But what I want to know is
is it enough God's portion that there’s מעילה? me'ilah? Oh, did I,
darn it, I pushed stop, I must have... Okay, כי קמיבעי
לי מעילה.
Ki kamiba'i
li me'ilah. What I want to know is מעילה. me'ilah. ופשיט הכי
לא ירדו ואין בהן מעילה. Upashit hachi lo yerdu v'ein bahen me'ilah.
Again, the conclusion was the same as ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, they
stay up there even though there is not yet מעילה. me'ilah. That
is the end of that discussion around ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. Now
we continue to wrap up the משנה. mishnah. ואלו לא היה פסולן
בקודש, V'eilu lo hayah psulan bakodesh, the following things their פסול psul
is not בקודש, bakodesh, and it lists all these things that basically
the invalidity happened to it when it was still alive. אמר רבי
יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Yochanan. And then רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says even
a בעל מום. ba'al mum. והגמרא, V'ha'Gemara, of course, immediately jumps in,
oh, דוקין שבעין, dukin she'ba'ayin, only a small little מום. mum. Okay,
it’s not necessarily what the משנה mishnah says, but it is how
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan explains רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, because why does
a מום mum get to be something more appropriate for the מזבח
mizbeach than these other types of problems? I mean מום mum is
explicit in the תורה. Torah. These other things, רובע, rovei'a, ונרבע, v'nirba,
etc., נעבד, ne'evad, a lot of these things are less explicit. So
because there’s no logic, I mean maybe you could say, you know,
מום mum is only physical, other things are moral or religiously problematic.
But anyway, it’s not a clear logic why מום mum should be
better. So therefore we limit the scope of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
to only a narrow category of
blemishes. לא הכשיר רבי עקיבא אלא בדוקין שבעין. Lo hechshir Rabbi Akiva
ela b'dukin she'ba'ayin. We’re only talking about some type of like cataracts
or blemish of the eye. So what makes that something that’s not
so bad? It’s still a blemish. הואיל וכשרים בעופות, Ho'il v'ksherim b'ofot,
because you
can, it’s okay by a bird. Because birds are only invalid if
it’s a, if it's missing a limb. So anything less than missing
a limb would be okay. Now, of course, the question is one
minute. There is a big gap between missing a limb and a
tiny little blemish of the eye, right? There all the standard blemishes
are not about missing a limb. So you could talk about a
huge obvious blemish. Why did you describe it as the most tiny
like, you know, hard to identify blemish if it really is what's
כשר kasher in a bird? What's כשר kasher in a bird is
anything that’s not missing a limb. So say as long as it’s
not missing a limb. So רש"י Rashi responds to this. If you
look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, הואיל וכשרים בעופות, Ho'il v'ksherim
b'ofot, the first narrow line. He says, דכתיב תמימים זכר בבקר בכבשים
ובעזים, D'chtiv tmimim zachar babakar bakshavim uva'izim, תמימות tmimut וזכרות, v'zachrut, unblemished
and maleness, בבהמה, bibhema,
that’s only required by בבקר, babakar, בכבשים, bakshavim, excuse me,
only by cattle and sheep. ואין תמימות וזכרות בעופות, V'ein tmimut v'zachrut
b'ofot,
birds doesn’t matter male or female and no blemish problem, so that's
the principle we don't care about blemishes. ומיהו מחוסר אבר לא, Umihu
mechusar eivar lo, but it can’t be missing a limb. משום הקריבהו
נא לפחתך. Mishum hakrivehu na l'pachatecha. Now again quoting the פסוק pasuk
we just quoted, that’s unseemly. Which is funny because the גמרא Gemara
in עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and elsewhere learns out that missing a
limb is no good because of a פסוק, pasuk, right? By נח,
Noach, which says להחיות אתך, l'hachayot itcha, חיים ולא שלמים chayim v'lo
sh'lemim etc. Anyway, so it's funny that רש"י Rashi frames the limb
problem as this it's unseemly. But רש"י Rashi has a reason for
framing it that way because this helps him explain why we're limiting
it to problems of the eye. Because then רש"י Rashi says וכן
v'chen or וכל מום מגונה. v'chol mum meguneh.
If the reason of missing a limb is not just a הלכה
halacha in missing a limb, it's that it's disgusting, so that would
include three words רש"י Rashi did this in. That would include any
type of obvious blemish, any type of repulsive blemish. So anything that
is too obvious, that is too aesthetically disgusting or whatever it is,
that would be included in something that would be invalid for a
bird. Such a חידוש. chiddush. We're always taught that birds, it's only
a limb problem. But in order to explain why we went all
the way to the other extreme to talk about a little problem
of the eye, רש"י Rashi says really by birds it's not limited
to limbs, it's limbs and major noticeable blemishes and that's.